So yeah. We today's דף daf. *daf* is נט *nun-tet* we pick
up at the very top of the דף daf *daf*. We are
doing the act of counting for מעשר בהמה Maaser Behema. *ma'aser behemah*.
We learned that there's a way you use a stick and paint
and so on walking through an opening but בדיעבד b'diavad, *bedi'avad* without
all of that it works as long as it's the tenth and
there's some type of counting maybe even a counting in your head
or we'll see a little bit more about that in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. But then you have the even more radical position of
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda*
that says that it doesn't even have to be the tenth. It
just has to be
10%, one-tenth, not the tenth. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says where
does he get it from? So he because it's העשירי *ha'asiri* which
means the tenth of some counting that is, you know, the tenth
of a list and he gets it from the fact that it's
connected to מעשר Maaser *ma'aser* of grain and מעשר Maaser *ma'aser* of
grain that's clearly the case. So we'll pick up with
that at the very top of נט עמוד א *nun-tet amud aleph*
that idea. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had said at the end
of yesterday that our maybe we'll read the last line of נח
עמוד ב amud bet. *nun-chet amud bet* כשם שהתרומה גדולה ניטלת באומד
ובמחשבה *Keshem shehatruma gedola niteles be'omed uv'machshava* we link תרומה Terumah *truma*
regular תרומה *truma* which you take there's no even percentage it's a
small any amount any tiny amount you want the rabbis give a
percentage anyway from your grain and you give it to the כהן
*kohen*. And that's linked to תרומת מעשר Terumat Maaser *trumas ma'aser* which
is the לויים *Levi'im* take from their 10% their מעשר Maaser, *ma'aser*
they take the 10% of their 10% so it's 1% of the
original amount and they give that to the כהנים *kohanim*. So the
their תרומת מעשר Maaser *trumas ma'aser* their 10% of 10% is linked
to a classic תרומה *truma*. Now the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of linking
it is that theirs is an exact amount 10%. Classic תרומה *truma*
is any amount. So and by linking it it allows for less
precision greater latitude when you're taking their תרומת מעשר Maaser. *trumas ma'aser*
when you're taking their 10% of 10%. So let's take a look.
So the same way the major תרומה *truma* can be given באומד
ובמחשבה *be'omed uv'machshava* estimating because of course you estimate there's not even
an exact amount and you can do it by thought you can
just sort of think that you know that little amount over there
at that side is תרומה *truma* you don't have to verbalize it
and so on.
But it is a תרומת מעשר Maaser. *trumas ma'aser* is a tenth
of that so it is more exact no?
No תרומה גדולה *truma gedola* is that way so now the top
of נט עמוד א *nun-tet amud aleph* אף תרומת מעשר Maaser. *af
trumas ma'aser* so even תרומת מעשר ma'aser *trumas ma'aser* which is which
is 10% ניטלת באומד ובמחשבה *niteles be'omed uv'machshava* can be done through
estimation you don't have to exactly measure 10% which is a חידוש
chiddush *chiddush* it's supposed to be 10% you think you'd have to
be precise and it can be and it can be ובמחשבה *uv'machshava*
it can be with thought. You don't have to articulate and designate
explicitly think say it you can just in your mind think that
that's that amount over there that is מעשר ma'aser. *ma'aser*. Now that
is תרומה *truma*. Now that gives you תרומה *truma* and תרומת מעשר
ma'aser. *trumas ma'aser* but now we have to move it next stage
you have to get it to מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser* because our case
is not תרומה *truma* but it's מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says ומעשר קרי רחמנא תרומה *uma'aser karei rachmana truma* and
מעשר ma'aser, *ma'aser* itself is called a type of a תרומה *truma*.
דכתיב *Dechtiv* the verse says דכתיב את מעשר ma'aser בני ישראל אשר
ירימו לה' תרומה *dechtiv es ma'aser bnei yisrael asher yarimu l'Hashem truma*
the tithing of בני ישראל *bnei yisrael* that they will lift up
to ה' *Hashem* as a תרומה *truma* נתתיו ללויים לנחלה *Nesativ l'Levi'im
l'nachala* I have given to the לויים *Levi'im* as an inheritance. So
now we see that not only is תרומת מעשר ma'aser *trumas ma'aser*
which is 10% of 10% can be estimated and can be thought
but even normal מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser* okay which is a חידוש chiddush
*chiddush* right because normally we're told you have to be very precise
about מעשר maiser? *ma'aser* you don't want to take too much you
don't want to take too little but here we're told that actually
there's an element of estimation.
Who told you to be so precise about מעשר maiser. *ma'aser*?
There's a משנה mishna. *mishna* where is it? There's a משנה mishna
*mishna* in פרקי
אבות *Pirkei Avos* I think it says אל תרבה לעשר אומדות *al
tarbe l'aser umadot* right which means that you're allowed to do it.
All right I understand I'm not saying it's contradicting that I'm just
saying the general principle is we try to be precise but nevertheless
you're allowed to do it if you estimate and
and more important for us is you can do it purely by
thought you don't have to do it actually by designating. So the
גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says והקיש מעשר בהמה Maaser Behema למעשר דגן *v'eikesh
ma'aser behemah l'ma'aser dagan* and now we're going to connect the מעשר
maiser? *ma'aser* of animals to the מעשר maiser. *ma'aser* of grain. מה
מעשר maiser, דגן ניטל באומד ובמחשבה *Ma ma'aser dagan nital be'omed uv'machshava*
the same way grain can be done that way by estimation and
by thought אף מעשר בהמה Maaser Behema ניטל באומד ובמחשבה *af ma'aser
behemah nital be'omed uv'machshava* even the מעשר בהמה Maaser Behema, *ma'aser behemah*.
So how does he know it doesn't have to be the tenth
based on this? Now I have to say that it exactly it
made a little bit of a shift meaning the emphasis until now
before you got to מעשר בהמה Maaser Behema *ma'aser behemah* was that
you didn't need to verbalize it
and maybe that's how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s understanding the primary חידוש
chidush *chiddush* of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda* when he says you just take one maybe he
does mean it's the tenth maybe he just means you do it
all in your head maybe his whole חידוש chidush *chiddush* is that
you don't have to articulate and verbalize it. We're going to see
in a minute how much has to be verbalized according to the
other opinion. So that's one element of the חידוש chidush. *chiddush* that
it could be by thought and it doesn't have to be verbalized.
But it seems the simple sense of what רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda* said is he's not
just saying you don't have to verbalize it he's even saying that
it doesn't have to be
the tenth. Well right the tenth way this precision is 10% but
it doesn't have to be the tenth it can be 10% and
maybe that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* means by the comparison because
by מעשר maiser דגן *ma'aser dagan* it's 10%. Maaser itself of course
it's not the tenth, you're not counting one-tenth, two-tenths, three-tenths and you
take the tenth-tenth, right? You just take any tenth. So maybe that's
what it really means to make it like מעשר. maiser And maybe
Michael's correct, that's the emphasis of like the lack of precision means
that the same way it doesn't have to be precisely 10%, it
also doesn't have to be exactly the tenth, it just has to
be a tenth. But again, it's not exactly clear. The parallel is
not is not the same. The aspect of אומד מחשבה omed machshava
is different than I think the point about whether it's a tenth
or the tenth. Yes.
Is there a תוספות Tosafot that you're quoting from page 88? Yes.
What is it?
No, it's really not it's really much more about the issue about
the grain and very little about our about our discussion. And all
these big תוספותס Tosafots are about the parameters of תרומה and מעשר
maiser, and תרומת מעשר maiser. and about those two principles. What exactly
is the limits or the parameters of אומד omed and what are
the parameters of מחשבה? machshava? But it really has you know very
little to do with connecting it to to our case of מעשר
maiser בהמה.
I just wanted to understand, if we're saying אומד omed and everything
here is everything is אומד במחשבה, omed b'machshava, so that means for
מעשר maiser, they don't really need to have 10%. You can have
like a little more, a little less. Is that what he's saying?
Well, that's right. I mean and so you you try to have
10%, you estimate 10%, but you don't have to but if you're
not precise, it's still good.
No, precise is in not necessarily like, you know, this is the
tenth and whatever, but even if you take let's say 11% or
9%.
Accidentally, but you try to take 10%. Right. So that and that's
exactly what this תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out, how far do
you go by saying that you can be off and so on.
Okay. So but again, but that's why it's not exactly relevant, it's
not exactly the same as our issue. Our issue is not being
off. Our issue is number one the issue, maybe it's the primary
concern of the גמרא Gemara about not verbalizing it. And number two,
that there's that that you don't have to do the tenth in
a sequence, but that 10% is enough. So both of those are
true by מעשר, maiser. but it's not exactly the same as the
aspect of אומד. omed. Okay, let's take a look as the גמרא
Gemara continues. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, can I get the tissues? Yes.
Does this replace the whole system that we were discussing about going
under the rod and one
by one?
Well, yeah, so it's I mean so this is the בדיעבד, bedi'avad
it's not לכתחילה. lechatchila. Ideally everybody just processes walks them single file
and go under the rod. This is a question about what at
the bare minimum would still count. So one one opinion was as
long as it's the tenth even if it's done without a rod
and even if it's done but you know but at least it
has to be the tenth in a sequence even if they're all
standing there and you're just counting them, but this opinion of רב
יוסי ברבי יהודה Rav Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda is even if it's not
the tenth of a sequence. Okay. So yeah, but that's only like
at at the bare minimum, not as the ideal.
So let's keep on going.
Okay. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. עשירי. Asiri. Now we get to a
point which I mentioned yesterday about תוספות Tosafot about where תוספות Tosafot
points out about how why isn't it considered like you're sanctifying on
יום טוב Yom Tov and תוספות Tosafot says well by מעשר maiser
בהמה you don't do you really sanctify and instill sanctity into the
animal or just by virtue of it being the tenth and counting
it as the tenth, that automatically makes it מעשר maiser and automatically
gives it קדושה kedusha but you didn't instill the קדושה. kedusha. So
now we're going to have a discussion essentially around that point. Let's
take a look. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, עשירי מאליו
הוא קדוש. asiri me'elav hu kadosh. The tenth one is sanctified automatically.
That sounds like the point I just said, you don't have to
say I'm sanctifying it, by counting it as number 10, it becomes
sanctified. But the גמרא Gemara or understands this even more than that,
even further, that even without counting it as number 10, it'll automatically
become מעשר. maiser. How does that happen? Let's take a look. מנא
ליה לרבא הא, Mena lei le-Rava ha, where does רבא Rava get
this? So אילימא מהא דתניא, ilima me-ha de-tanya, אין לי אלא שקרא
שמו עשירי. ein li ela she-kara shemo asiri. I only know, says
the ברייתא braita that we learned yesterday, when you call it the
tenth that it's מעשר. maiser לא קרא שמו עשירי מנין, lo kara
shemo asiri minayin, if you didn't call it the tenth how do
you know? תלמוד לומר עשירי יהיה קודש, talmud lomar asiri yihiyeh kodesh,
it would be קודש kodesh מכל מקום mi-kol makom regardless. So you
don't even have to call it the tenth. So what does it
mean not calling it? So yesterday I suggested it might mean that
you mentally designate it as that, but that you know the גמרא
Gemara has been emphasizing the the mental aspect to רב יוסי ברבי
יהודה. Rav Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda. So what does it mean you didn't
call it the tenth? So let's take a look. ודילמא עשירי הוא
דלא קריה קדוש קריה. ve-dilma asiri hu de-la karia kadosh karia. Maybe
he didn't call it ten, but maybe he did still say it's
holy, it's sanctified. So the גמרא's Gemara understanding that what רבא Rava
says it's automatically קדוש, kadosh, what it means is the following, meaning
it's never spelled out explicitly but it's implicit and רש"י Rashi says,
it means let's say I have 10 animals in my pen and
they're walking through and one through nine walks through and the tenth
is left there and he hasn't walked through and I don't do
anything. I say great, I'm done, I go home. Okay. So it's
clear that this is the tenth, but I didn't designate it as
the tenth, I didn't say anything. So this is going even further
than the point yesterday. The point yesterday was that by calling it
the tenth even without sanctifying it it becomes מעשר. maiser, Here the
point is that if it's self-evident that it's the tenth then it
is that defines it as the tenth even without any designation. So
the גמרא Gemara says isn't that the point of the ברייתא braita
we said yesterday that even if you don't call it the tenth?
Says well, he didn't call it the tenth, but doesn't mean he
didn't designate it. at all, maybe you said קדוש, kadosh, maybe you
said something to designate it. So let's keep on going. אלא מהא
דתניא
Ela
mehadetanya from the following ברייתא. braita. קרא לתשיעי
עשירי, Kara lateshi'i asiri, you accidentally called the ninth the tenth, you
got mixed up in your counting.
ויצא העשירי ולא דיבר, Veyatza ha'asiri velo diber, and then the tenth
one came out and you didn't say anything because, you know, you
thought you were sort of done. You said for nine, you said
ten, and then ten walked out, whatever, you didn't bother saying anything.
התשיעי נאכל במומו, Hateshi'i ne'echal bemumo, so here's a הלכה. halacha. The
הלכה halacha which we're going to see later, but I mean it's
brought in here, is that if you're the מעשר ma'aser. has the
ability to have to to affect the animal before it and after
it. So if you but if you make a mistake. If you
accidentally call nine ten or you call eleven ten, they also become
a type of a מעשר. ma'aser. The follow this is the following
difference. If you accidentally call nine ten, then it becomes קדושת מעשר
kedushat ma'aser but you can't bring it as a קרבן. korban. So
you have to wait for it to get a blemish and you
eat it outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. If you accidentally call
eleven ten, you even can bring it as a קרבן. korban. I'll
discuss why in a few minutes. Okay, so here what happened is
the ninth one you accidentally called ten, so that's the הלכה halacha
that it's it has קדושה, kedusha, you eat it with a blemish.
Okay, now what do you do with the tenth?
והעשירי מעשר, Veha'asiri ma'aser, the tenth is מעשר. ma'aser. So this is
exactly the example of רבא. Rava. You didn't say anything about the
tenth, but it was the tenth, the reality defined it as the
tenth and it became מעשר ma'aser, even though you didn't designate. You
even did worse, you even called the wrong thing מעשר ma'aser.
and this one never even walked out. Is it the same thing?
That might maybe not, but right now we're talking about you didn't
do something opposite it, you just didn't positively do it. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא
שאני התם דאיעבר ליה עשירי, Udilma shani hatam de'ivra lei asiri, maybe
that's different that the tenth one has been selected. What does that
mean? Well, let's just read the other answer. אינמי דאחוי ליה, Inami
de'achvei lei, or you or you signaled, you designated. Now the second
answer is easy. The second answer means you don't have to verbalize
it, but you have to maybe do, you know, do that or
do, you know, like that or something, you know, you did some
signal that showed it. That maybe is needed. That but it didn't
it just said you didn't speak, it didn't say you didn't do
anything to designate. But what is the previous answer, דאיעבר ליה? de'ivra
lei? So רש"י Rashi says that that means that it did in
the end walk out as the tenth in the line and רבא's
Rava חידוש chiddush. was maybe even further. רבא's Rava חידוש chiddush was
nine walked out of the pen and the tenth one was left
in the pen. So now but once, you know, once you're debating
that, then you're basically agreeing in principle. You're just arguing over the
details. Meaning you're basically saying you're right, it doesn't need a designation,
it can be automatically defined as the tenth based on the reality
of what's happening. And then you just debate what are the details
to be defined as tenth. If it walks out tenth in the
line, then clearly it's defined as tenth. If it's left as the
tenth one in the pen, then we can define is that defined
as tenth in a sequence because it never actually walked out? Okay,
so those two answers are radically different. One answer basically, you know,
grants the principle of the thing. You're right, you don't have to
designate, it can automatically be tenth, but not every case is the
tenth of a sequence. Left in the pen is not the same
as walking out number ten. That's the first answer. The second answer
is, no, maybe you still have to designate it, it just doesn't
have to be a verbal designation. I should say by the way
that the גמרא Gemara is consistent before with without רבא Rava sort
of says, you know, that it's automatically defined or whatever. The גמרא
Gemara here claims to be saying, you know, it's talking about like
pointing or whatever, that mental designation doesn't count. So that again I'm
just going back on רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda,
it sounds like, you know, part of the חידוש chiddush. of רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה was the מחשבה, machshava, was the fact that it
was just purely in your head. Because here the גמרא Gemara within
this discussion is assuming you do verbal or physical designating, or even
according to רבא, Rava, it's at least somehow self-evident by the reality.
So it seems like a major part of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
was not just ten percent rather than the tenth of a sequence,
but also the fact that it was purely mental. Okay, so now
we continue. So we haven't yet really fully proven רבא's Rava case
about when it that it can automatically be the tenth. Let's take
a look.
אלא מהא דתניא, Ela mehadetanya, the following thing we taught in a
ברייתא. braita. קרא לתשיעי עשירי, Kara lateshi'i asiri, you called the ninth
the tenth by mistake once again, and we said that that gives
it the קדושה kedusha of מעשר, ma'aser,
but it can't be eat it can't be
brought as a קרבן. korban. ומת עשירי בדיר, Umet asiri bedir, and
the tenth one died in the pen. Okay, so you never got
around to actually taking מעשר ma'aser. of the animals, right? You had
what happened, you had ten, nine walked out, you called the ninth
accidentally the tenth, the tenth one which if it would have walked
out would have been the מעשר maaser died in the pen. So
what does what's the
הלכה? halacha?
ומת, Umet, right then and there.
Right then and there, yeah, dropped dead before it walked out. Okay,
תשיעי נאכל במומו, Teshi'i ne'echal bemumo, the ninth one is because you
called it the tenth has קדושת מעשר kedushat ma'aser and is eaten
with a blemish outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. וכולם פטורים, Vechulam
peturim, but they're all the rest are exempt. Now the question is
why are the rest exempt? You never took מעשר maaser, from these
animals. So why are the first eight animals exempt if you didn't
actually take מעשר? maaser So we're assuming you did take מעשר. maaser
Why did you take מעשר? maaser Because the tenth one that was
left in the pen, that automatically became the מעשר.
maaser But then you don't have to take מעשר, maaser right?
No, but you mean you don't have to combine them with the
next with the next deer, meaning even if you have other animals
born that year, they're off the hook. So מאי טעמא כולם פטורים,
mai ta'ama kulom p'turim, why are they all exempt?
Like, there was never מעשר maaser taken. אלא לאו משום דקדיש ליה
עשירי, ela lav mishum d'kadish lei asiri, the
tenth one, although it died in the pen, automatically became sanctified. The
גמרא Gemara says no, ודילמא דאיפטרו במנין הראוי, v'dilma d'iptru b'minyan harauy,
maybe they were exempt because they were part of a fit counting.
דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava, because רבא Rava says, מנין הראוי פוטר, minyan
harauy poter, a fit counting exempts. What does that mean? This is
going to be most of our discussion on the
עמוד ב. It means that if I have only seven animals, let's
say in the pen, I don't have ten, and I count one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven, it was a meaningless counting. And
if I get more animals during this same year, I have to
combine them and do מעשר maaser again. But let's say I have
ten animals in a pen, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
and then I don't know, let's say the whole last three die.
Okay? So because those first seven were מנין הראוי, minyan harauy, they
were a counting that was fit to be the process of מעשר,
maaser because when I started the counting, there were ten animals. So
it was a meaningful count, it was fit to lead up to
מעשר. maaser Once you've been through the process, you're out of the
category. So those seven never have to take מעשר maaser from them
again, although I never wound up taking מעשר, maaser but they were
part of a legitimate process. That's called
מנין הראוי. minyan harauy. Something like that. Well, actually the גמרא Gemara
is going to say once it's over תחת השבט, tachat hashevet, it's
not over again. Once it went through the process, it's like no
double jeopardy, almost. Okay? So,
so therefore he says, ah, this case, nine went through, the tenth
died, the other eight are exempt. It's not because the tenth was
automatically מעשר. maaser You don't need it to be מעשר maaser to
exempt the animals that already went through the process. They're exempt because
of מנין הראוי. minyan harauy. As soon as you go through the
process, you're exempt even if the מעשר maaser never wound up being
taken in the end. So that does not prove that the tenth
one left in the pen was מעשר.
maaser Only the ones that have actually been counted.
Only the ones that have actually been counted.
So the one that's in line, the last seven,
six, you still have to be combined for מעשר maaser of the
next time, like during the same year.
According to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili or whoever it was,
רבי
יוסי ברבי
יהודה, would he also say that like even if I started like
thinking in my mind and then three died, would he go that
far?
It's for him maybe
a מנין הראוי minyan harauy as soon as he allows that to
begin with?
It's an interesting question.
It's an interesting question what would constitute מנין minyan for him. Again,
I don't know if according to him it's an idea of the
tenth or just the tenth or one tenth. If it's not an
idea if you don't even בדיעבד need the tenth, so the act
of מנין minyan maybe isn't even as significant for him. So that's
a good question. Dov, you had a question? No? Okay. James, you
had a question? James has said that it only applies to the
ones that actually were counted, not the ones that were left in
the pen. If you counted one, two, three, and then I don't
know, number four died, so now you don't have ten to do
מעשר, maaser so you stop the whole process. Numbers five through ten
that are left in the pen are not exempt. It's only the
ones that actually were counted, okay, not the ones that were just,
you know, put in the pen. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, okay, אלא
מהא, ela meha,
from the following ברייתא baraita we'll try to prove this idea that
the tenth one can automatically become קדוש. kadosh. קרא לתשיעי עשירי, kara
l'tshii asiri,
so you counted the ninth the tenth, like we said before, והניח
עשירי בדיר, v'hiniach asiri b'dir,
and the tenth is left in the pen. So what's the הלכה?
halacha? התשיעי נאכל במומו, hatshii ne'echal b'mumo, the ninth one is eaten
with a blemish because again it has קדושת מעשר, kedushas ma'aser, it
can't be brought. והעשירי מעשר, v'ha'asiri ma'aser, and the tenth is brought
as מעשר. maaser So there you go, a ברייתא baraita that explicitly
says רבא's Rava הלכה. halacha. You count nine, tenth one is left,
tenth one automatically becomes מעשר. mayser Not only, no, the did not
say the tenth became מעשר. mayser So you'll see the others did
not say that. This explicitly says that the tenth one automatically, and
not only did it automatically become מעשר, mayser even in the face
of the fact that you called something else מעשר. mayser Nevertheless, since
this was in fact the tenth, even before walking out, where the
other case was that it walked out, יצא. yatza. This was not
יצא. yatza. This was left in the pen. So there you go.
So we're done. רבא's Rava position is proved by a ברייתא. baraita.
And now we move on. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, מעשר, mayser I'm sorry,
והתניא, v'hatanya, now the גמרא Gemara is no longer dealing with רבא,
Rava, it's dealing now with just with analyzing the ברייתא baraita we
just quoted. תשיעי חולין, tshii chullin, so now we've left talking about
the tenth that that automatically becomes מעשר. mayser, We're talking about now
the ninth. You called nine ten. So here, although we've got a
lot of ברייתות baraitas here that when you say call nine ten,
it automatically gets קדושת מעשר. kedushas ma'aser. But now we have a
ברייתא baraita that says if you call nine ten, it's not sanctified,
it has no, it doesn't affect its status. So what's the story
with number nine if you miscount? So תני תנא קמיה דרב ששת.
tani tanna kamei d'Rav Sheshet. So a תני תנא קמיה דרב ששת,
Tani Tana kamei deRav Sheshet, הא מני? Ha Mani? This ברייתא Baraita
that says nine is not sanctified if you miscounted? רבי שמעון בן
יהודה היא. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda hi. It's רבי שמעון בן יהודה.
Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda. דתניא, DeTanya, we've done a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי
שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer
mishum Rabbi Shimon, which denotes the ורבי שמעון, V-Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, אף על פי שאינו קדוש אלא
אם כן נעקר שם עשירי הימנו. Af al pi she'eino kadosh ela
im kein ne'ekar shem asiri heimenu.
So the ninth one is not sanctified unless you uproot the name
of the tenth from it. What does this mean? What it means
is, hold on, I'm so sorry. Right.
It means like this. It means remember I told you that both
number nine and number 11 can become sanctified if you miscall them.
And I also told you that there's a special הלכה Halacha that
when you miscall number 11 ten, not only is it sanctified, it
can even be brought as a קרבן. Korban. Now part of the
reason for that is that it's building on a model of תמורה.
Temura. What's the model of תמורה? Temura? I have a קרבן שלמים,
Korban Shlamim, I have another animal, I'm not allowed to say I'm
exchanging A for B. That's a לאו דאורייתא. Lav De'Oraisa. That's going
to be a מסכת Masechet we're about going to learn very soon.
Okay, if I did say it, however, the other animal also becomes
קדוש Kadosh and not only that, under most circumstances I can even
bring the other animal as a קרבן. Korban. I do bring it
as a קרבן, Korban, not just becomes קדוש, Kadosh, I actually bring
it as a קרבן. Korban. So when I call number 11 ten,
there's an aspect there of תמורה, Temura, right? There's an aspect of
sort of, I'm not exactly saying I'm taking the קדושה Kedusha from
this and putting it on that, but I'm sort of saying this
is taking the place of the other one, okay, by calling this
ten. So because 11 is a תמורה, Temura, it actually is a
type of תמורה, Temura, it gets brought as a קרבן. Korban. Now
why is nine not a תמורה? Temura? Why is nine, it's קדוש
Kadosh but it's not brought? Why is it not the same?
There's no way it could ever have been the tenth because it
was only ninth.
There's no tenth to start from! Right, there's only, it's only nine.
So I can't really be starting from the thing that's really קדוש.
Kadosh. So because I called it ten, it gives it that קדושה
Kedusha to be sanctified but not brought as a קרבן. Korban. But
the 11 where ten already exists, right, that can actually become, that
actually can get fully sanctified and be brought as a קרבן. Korban.
That's why 11 is brought as a קרבן, Korban, number one. But
number two, what's also required for 11 to be brought as a
קרבן Korban
is
that you have to be עוקר שם עשירי Oker shem asiri from
number ten. Because what am I trying to do when I do
תמורה? Temura? When I try to do תמורה, Temura, I try to
say I'm removing the קדושה Kedusha from this animal and placing it
on this. So if I basically said number ten came out and
I said ten, and number 11 came out and I said ten,
right, I'm not clearly trying to remove the קדושה Kedusha from number
ten, right? I'm just also trying to call 11 ten. So the
only way 11 becomes קדוש Kadosh to be brought as a קרבן
Korban is if when number ten comes out I call it nine.
And when number 11 comes out I call it ten. When number
ten comes out, when number ten comes out I call it nine
or 11 maybe, right, okay, and when number 11 comes out I
call it ten. Because then what I'm trying to do is I'm
trying to say although this is the tenth, and now we actually
have just learned from רבא Rava that even without me calling it
the tenth it becomes קדוש, Kadosh, right, so although this is the
tenth, I am removing its status, right, rejecting that status and I'm
trying to place it on 11. So 11, so that's when 11
becomes able to be brought as a קרבן. Korban. Ten is still
קדושה, Kedusha, ten is still a קרבן, Korban, but then it's exactly
following the model of תמורה. Temura. Because the idea of the model
of תמורה, Temura, although it's a prohibition, and it's not exactly clear
here that you've done the לאו Lav of תמורה, Temura, but the
model that the second animal becomes equally sanctified and is brought as
a קרבן Korban is when you're trying to remove it from קרבן
Korban one and to place it on קרבן Korban two. So following
that model we say 11, because ten already exists, 11 can get
the full sanctity and be brought as a קרבן, Korban, but only
when you're עוקר שם עשירי. Oker shem asiri. It doesn't affect it,
the tenth is קדוש Kadosh like in תמורה Temura it's not affected,
the original isn't affected, but you have to miscall it. Okay, so
that's the assumptions we're working with. And now we're going to see
the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that number nine
is also doesn't get any sanctity unless you mislabel number ten. By
analogy to the case of ten and 11, he says nine and
ten is the same. Nine doesn't get any קדושה Kedusha unless you
mislabel number ten.
But what's exactly that? You're trying to remove the קדושה Kedusha from
number ten which means there was קדושה Kedusha on it because you
once designated it as such. But if I called number nine nine,
number ten nine, number 11 nine, I haven't called anything number ten.
Yeah but but now at least we have, I don't know how
we would have explained it before רבא, Rava, but now given רבא
Rava it makes sense because according to רבא, Rava, ten is קדוש
Kadosh regardless of what I call it.
No correct, but that's because you already didn't do anything or it's,
you know, but that's like, you know, sort of like a שב
ואל תעשה. Shev ve'Al Ta'aseh. Here is sort of like a קום
ועשה Kum ve'Aseh that you're trying to lead in the other way.
I understand and now I'm telling you and now I'm telling you
that that doesn't matter. That now we see exactly that ten walks
out, I call it nine, it's still ten, and that and then
but because I'm trying to uproot it and then I wind up
calling 11 ten. So that's exactly the point. Again, I'm not sure
how we would explain that without רבא, Rava, okay, but once רבא
Rava gives us the basis to say that it's automatically קדוש, Kadosh,
now we understand how this system works. Okay, so let's take a
look.
Even number nine is קדוש Kadosh only if you uproot the name
of ten. You mislabel ten. And that maybe gives more weight to
your calling number nine, to your designating number nine as ten, is
because you also misdesignated number ten.
If I call nine ten and call ten ten,
then according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, nine is not קדוש. Kadosh.
Okay, so that's
why we've been saying nine is קדוש Kadosh if you call it
ten, here a ברייתא Braita says nine is not קדוש. Kadosh. So,
oh, that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's position. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon thinks
that even nine doesn't become קדוש Kadosh unless you also mislabel
ten. והדין נותן V'hadin noten and now he's going to say, and
that actually the logic dictates that. ומה אחד עשר שהוא עושה קדושה
ליקרב, Umah achad asar shehu oseh kedusha l'hikarev, the eleventh that becomes
so holy it can be brought as a קרבן Korban and therefore
it's very weighty, אינו קדוש אלא אם כן נעקר שם עשירי הימנו,
eino kadosh ela im ken ne'ekar shem asiri heimenu, so even though
it's very weighty and you might say that it's
more prepared to become sanctified, nevertheless it does not become sanctified unless
you uproot number ten from ten. תשע, Tesha, the number nine, that's
much lighter קדושה, Kedusha, שאינו עושה קדושה ליקרב, she'eino oseh kedusha l'hikarev,
so maybe the assumption being, we'll see the גמרא Gemara will say
the exact opposite, but the assumption being if it's a lighter קדושה,
Kedusha, so then maybe it's not so susceptible to become קדוש Kadosh
because it's not so weighty. So אינו דין שיהא נעקר שם עשירי
הימנו אם לא לא? eino din she-yehei ne'ekar shem asiri heimenu im
lo lo? Doesn't it make sense that number nine would only become
קדוש Kadosh if you uproot number ten? Meaning if eleven, which has
a more serious
קדושה, Kedusha, nevertheless it only happens when you uproot number ten, nine
which is less serious should also only happen if you uproot number
ten. Of course the גמרא Gemara says, what are you talking about?
It's the opposite. So the גמרא Gemara says,
where
was I? אם לא לא. im lo lo. השתא, Hashta, what do
you mean? Exactly what you said explains why is the reason why
to say the exact opposite. אחד עשר שהוא עושה קדושה ליקרב, Achad
asar shehu oseh kedusha l'hikarev, the eleventh, which is a serious קדושה,
Kedusha, it allows it to be brought as a קרבן, Korban, so
in order to achieve that serious level of קדושה, Kedusha, אם נעקר
שם עשירי הימנו אין לא לא, im ne'ekar shem asiri heimenu in
lo lo, it will only achieve that serious level of קדושה Kedusha
if you're really trying to fully transfer the קדושה Kedusha from number
ten and it'll only do it if you mislabel ten. So how
can eleven get the full קדושה Kedusha of number ten if you're
really trying to uproot the קדושה Kedusha from ten and you've mislabeled
ten? תשע שאינו עושה קדושה ליקרב, Tesha she'eino oseh kedusha l'hikarev, nine,
which is not getting the קדושה Kedusha to be brought as a
קרבן, Korban, so you don't need to do as much to get
that lower level of קדושה. Kedusha. אף על גב דלא נעקר שם
עשירי הימנו, Af al gav d'lo ne'ekar shem asiri heimenu, even if
you didn't uproot the name of number ten, even if you didn't
mislabel number
ten. אי נמי, Ee nami, אחד עשר דאית ליה עשירי, achad asar
d'it lei asiri, okay that's argument number one. Argument number one is,
of course, you have to, by eleven where you're getting a high
level of
קדושה, Kedusha, you have to really be trying to transfer the קדושה
Kedusha from number ten. You have to be mislabeling it. Number nine,
where it's not such a high level, you don't have to really
be attempting to transfer the קדושה Kedusha of ten and to mislabel
ten. That's point number one why you should not need
mislabeling for nine to become קדוש. Kadosh. אי נמי, Ee nami, and
in addition you could say, אחד עשר דהויא ליה עשירי, achad asar
d'havya lei asiri, by number eleven, ten has already been counted. So
therefore eleven is competing with something,
ten has already walked out the door. To call eleven קדוש Kadosh
is very hard if ten has already been designated. It's got the
competition is there. So the only way eleven can become קדוש Kadosh
is if you undercut the competition a little bit, is if you
mislabel number ten. So אם נעקר שם עשירי הימנו אין לא לא.
im ne'ekar shem asiri heimenu in lo lo. That's only if you
mislabel number ten because ten is already there. תשע, Tesha, nine, has
no competition. Nine walked out the door, ten hasn't been counted yet.
It's much easier for nine to become קדוש Kadosh if there's nothing
else competing with it. דאכתי לא הויא ליה עשירי, D'achti lo havya
lei asiri, the tenth has not yet been designated. ואף על גב
דלא נעקר שם עשירי הימנו, Ve-af al gav d'lo ne'ekar shem asiri
heimenu, even if you did not uproot the name of the tenth,
nine is קדוש Kadosh without mislabeling number ten. And the גמרא Gemara
says ותו לא מידי, ve-tu lo midi, and it's not worth discussing
any further. I
mean, there's no logic to say what you said. You said, oh,
if eleven you have to mislabel ten, nine you have to mislabel
ten. What are you talking about? Eleven has a higher קדושה, Kedusha,
so to achieve that higher קדושה, Kedusha, you have to really try
to be transferring it from number ten. And eleven has competition, so
you got to mislabel ten. Nine is lower קדושה, Kedusha, no competition.
So as soon as you call nine ten, it's קדוש, Kadosh, even
if you don't mislabel number ten. So we're rejecting רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, right?
And you bring this as a קרבן? Korban?
And no, that's the point, though. Nine has a lower קדושה. Kedusha.
Because ten does not exist yet, they're arguing on units. It's
about whether it's got any קדושה, Kedusha, right? We usually outright reject
רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon.
I know, it is interesting. Yes.
Is there another perspective where you might think that the eleven should
even if there's a mistake that
after... Right, right.
Oh, so you're saying if you do if you misdo that, then
what happens, then how does that affect the next, the next counting?
Including 11 in, in 10.
Right, right. Yeah, I have to double check, but I think the
assumption is that if you actually have
misdone this in a way that sanctifies number 11, then yes, then
obviously it's not counted with the next group. I mean, you're right,
the implications would be if you had exactly
20 and you miscounted 11 and you called it 10 and it
had the קדושה kedusha and you did all this stuff that gave
11 the קדושה, kedusha, do you get out of taking מעשר mayser.
בהמה from the remaining nine?
Yeah, it's an interesting point. I mean, you presumably would because you
don't take מעשר mayser. בהמה, you only take it from חולין, chullin,
not from קדשים. kodshim. And now that you've managed to sanctify
11, you don't have 10 חולין chullin animals left to take מעשר
mayser בהמה from. You're right. It does have that ripple effect.
And those nine don't start with the next tier, right?
No, they would because they're still left in the pen. They never
went through the process. Okay, and now actually that's what we're going
to talk about the rest of the דף. Now the rest of
the דף is going to be this חידוש chiddush, of רבא Rava
about מנין הראוי. minyan haraui. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said רבא, Rava,
מנין הראוי פוטר. minyan haraui poter. So this exactly what we said,
that when animals have been counted, even if you never wound up
getting to number 10 because of some, as long as you were
in the process of getting to 10. It's not like you started
with seven animals, but as long as you were in the process,
even if you didn't wind up getting to number 10, once animals
have been through the process, no double jeopardy. They don't go through
it again. Okay, מנא ליה לרבא הא? Mena leh leRava ha? Where
does רבא Rava get this? אילימא מהא דתנן Elima meha detnan from
our משנה. mishna Our משנה mishna says, קפץ אחד מן המנויין לתוכן,
kafatz echad min haminuyin letochan, after you've counted them one of the
counted animals jumped back into the pen. So therefore now you stop
counting because one animal you can't recount, so you have to, so
everything is a ספק, safek, so you don't, so you stop. That's
what the משנה mishna said, כולם פטורים, kulam peturim, they're all exempt.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מנויין גופא דאיפטרו.
minuyin
gufa de'iptaru. How come the one that's counted is exempt? לאו מנין
הראוי? Lav minyan haraui? Doesn't this show רבא's Rava idea? It's exempt
because it's been counted. So this is exactly רבא's Rava point. The
משנה mishna says if one of the counted ones jumped back, that
one's exempt, so now they're all exempt because you don't know which
is which. So you see that once it's been counted, it's exempt.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no. ודילמא דאיעשוריה. Udilma de'iasurei. No,
maybe it means that it was counted but then מעשר mayser, was
taken. Meaning if I had 30 animals and the first 10 I
counted and I did number 10 and that was מעשר, ma'aser, then
of 1 through 9 of which מעשר ma'aser. has been taken because
I did count number 10, one of those jumped back into the
remaining 20. We all agree that if you actually wound up taking
מעשר ma'aser. that the first nine,
you never use them again. רבא's Rava חידוש chiddush? was even if
you never got around to taking number 10. So although the משנה
mishna says if one of the counted ones jumped back, they're all
exempt because it's exempt, that might have been one of the counted
ones that eventually מעשר ma'aser, was taken. It does not prove רבא's
Rava point, which is if it was counted without מעשר having been
taken. So let's keep on going.
So the one comes out, you count it, one back in, everything
else is exempt.
According to רבא, Rava, absolutely correct. As soon as the process began
and it was, could have been completed, again, not that you started
with less than 10, then it automatically hit, it's exempt as soon
as it's counted. Okay, that's רבא's Rava חידוש. chiddush? Okay, so let's
take a look. The גמרא gemara continues. So the גמרא gemara says
like this. ודילמא דאיעשוריה ההיא אמרת הסברא? Udilma de'iasurei hahi amrat hasvara?
No, you can't tell me that it was already taken מעשר when
it says the counted one jumps back. התניא מן המעושרים לתוכן? Hatenya
min hameusarim letochan? Because the next thing says, discusses if one of
the מעושרים meusarim jumped back. And we're understanding this phrase מעושרים meusarim
means animals from which מעשר was taken. So first the משנה mishna
says if one of the counted ones jumps back and then it
says if one of the מעושרים, meusarim, the מעשרed ones, come jump
back. So what does מעשרed mean? Does it mean part of the
group from which מעשר was taken or does it mean what's more
obvious, the actual tenth one? So now the גמרא gemara thinks it
means part of the group from which מעשר was taken. And if
that's what מעשרed means, then counted means even if מעשר wasn't taken.
Then they're separate lessons?
No, one of the ones counted without מעשר having been taken, רבא's
Rava case.
And then it's saying wouldn't it be obvious if you've
counted
10 if one of them jumped... I know. Not only would it
have been obvious, it's clearly the wrong read of the משנה Mishna
as the גמרא Gemara is about to say. So let's let the
גמרא Gemara reject it. So the גמרא says, ודילמא מאי מעושרים? Udilma
mai meusarim? Maybe when it says מעשרed, maybe what does that mean?
מעשר דוקא. Maaser davka. It means that it actually was the מעשר
one. And maybe, and then the גמרא says, דיקא נמי. Deika nami.
You know what? Actually that's פשט. pshat. That is true. That's what
the משנה mishna means. It's inferred from the language. דקתני. Dikatani. Because
what's the
הלכה? halacha? ירעו. Yiru. משנה mishna says if the מעשרed one jumps
back, so then you can't eat, they all are ספק מעשר safek
maaser and you have to wait for them all to get a
blemish. So obviously we're talking about the real מעשר is back there,
not just a counted one. Okay, so from our משנה mishnah you
can't prove רבא's Rava case because our משנה mishnah, says either מעשר
jumps back... or a counted one but it might be a counted
one that has been מעשר-ed, that has מעשר taken from the group.
We don't know רבא's Rava case of counted without מעשר being taken.
So אלא אמר רבא, elo amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava said
אמר קרא, amar kra, you're right, I don't get it from a
משנה or ברייתא. braisa. I get it from a פסוק. pasuk. Now
this by the way is fascinating because normally
it's the תנאים tannaim that you know דרשן darshan פסוקים. psukim. Normally
the אמוראים amoraim just interpret you know the words of the תנאים.
tannaim. But every now and then you get אמוראים amoraim דרשנינג darshaning
פסוקים psukim and I think רבא Rava does it more, a lot
more frequently than other אמוראים. amoraim. So it's an interesting thing to
look into, but here you know רבא's Rava saying you're right, I
have no evidence from earlier משניות mishnayos or ברייתות braisos and not
only do I not have any evidence you know but I'm also
actually going to say that it's my own דרשה drasha or that's
my own understanding of the פסוק. pasuk. What?
רבא Rava was on the cusp?
No, no, רב Rav was on the cusp. רבא Rava was very
late. So the גמרא says אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says
יעבור, ya'avor, shall pass by, shall pass under the staff, ולא שכבר
עבר, v'lo shekvar avar, but not that's already passed under. Once you're
once you're counted you're not counted again. מה שכבר עבר? mah shekvar
avar? And what would that mean? אי דאסירי ליה, id'asiri lei, if
it means that it's already מעשר's been taken from the group, צריכה
למימר? tzericha l'maymar? You wouldn't need the פסוק pasuk to tell you
that. Of course you know of course you'd say once you've taken
מעשר from the group you don't take again. Then you'll you'll always
be taking מעשר, you know you'll keep on taking again and again
and again. So obviously once you've taken you don't do it again.
So if the verse nevertheless has to exclude a case of having
counted, so אלא לאו דאיפטרו במנין ראוי. ela lav de'iftaru b'minyan rauy.
So rather if the פסוק pasuk is telling you you're excluded once
you're counted it must be a חידוש. A חידוש is even if
you have not gotten around to taking מעשר. And the גמרא says
שמע מינה. shma mina. That's a good proof which is amazing again
just that language שמע מינה. shma mina. You know שמע מינה's shma
mina normally if you're trying to prove something from a ברייתא, braisa,
משנה, you've made your argument, here you're just doing a דרשה drasha
and he says oh yeah that's good that's good proof. Okay so
now the גמרא says תני כוותיה דרבא, tani kevasei d'Rava, we learned
like רבא Rava which is quite impressive why if he's תני כוותיה
דרבא tani kevasei d'Rava he didn't quote the following ברייתא braisa to
support himself. Okay anyway היו לו עשרה טלאים והכניסן לדיר, hayu lo
asar tloim v'hichnisam l'dyer, you have ten sheep and you put them
into the pen, ומנה חמשה ומת אחד מהם, u'mana chamisha u'meis echad
meihem, and you counted five and then one of the remaining ones
died. So well no it's
actually going to it's actually going to discuss the different possibilities. Okay
one of them died, here's the cases: אם מן המנויין מת, im
min haminuyin meis, so if one of the ones you've already counted
died, so מונו משלים עליהם, munu mashlim aleihem, so you still so
fine who cares? You know when he counted it was part of
a series of ten, now it's dead who cares? There's still five
left in the pen, you keep on counting and number ten is
מעשר. Who cares if one of the ones that's already been counted
died.
It's really one of the nine I mean so to speak.
Right by the time you get to ten there's only nine that
are alive but when you counted it איתקן הוא it-kan-hu it was
alive and therefore that's enough. That's that. But אם משאינו מנויין מת,
im mishe'aino minuyin meis, but if one of the ones left in
the pen dies then
מנויין פטורין ומשאינו מנויין יצטרפו לגורן אחר. minuyin pturin v'she'aino minuyin istarfum
l'goren acher. This is exactly רבא's Rava חידוש. Okay one in left
in the pen dies, you're not now going to be able to
finish, right? There's only now going to be nine, you're never going
to get to a ten, there's only four left. But so the
ones that were already counted though are exempt. When you counted the
first five you had the ability to end at ten. Now so
those are now you never count again. The four that are left
alive in the pen those you have to now combine with the
next cycle and and do another מעשר from them. Okay so that's
exactly רבא's Rava חידוש, once you're counted if it was possible to
finish those are exempt even if you did not succeed in finishing.
Okay ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, now רבא Rava says now we're just
going to have a couple of scenarios like this, this will be
fun and easy. Okay היו לו יד טלאים, hayu lo yud dalet
tloim, you had fourteen sheep והכניסן לדיר v'hichnisam l'dyer and you put
them into a pen ויצאו ששה בפתח זה וארבעה בפתח זה. v'yatzu
shisha b'pesach zeh v'arba b'pesach zeh. Six went out of one door
and four went out of the other door. You you made a
big mistake, you left another door open. Okay now this is sequential.
So there's fourteen, first six go out, okay then four go out.
Now when the רמב"ם Rambam quotes this case he says as they
were going out of each door you were counting them. So when
they were going out of this door you're going one two three
four five six and when they're going out of that door right
maybe you thought you would like sort of you know process it
quicker so you had two people and each one was doing a
counting or something like that. Okay okay but so when the six
went out they could have been finished right because there were eight
left eight left. The four went out they were not part of
a process that could have been finished with the ten, right? Because
there was only eight and they went out of their separate that
was a separate counting because they went out of a separate exit.
So here's the הלכה. halakha.
What?
You didn't count those four seven eight nine ten, you count those
four one two three four separate counting.
Okay what?
Well let's take a look. So וארבעה נשתיירו שם v'arba nishtayru sham
and four are left in the pen. אותם ארבעה, osam arba, those
four where are they where which door are they heading out of?
The four
that are left in the pen. אם בפתח הששה יצאו, im b'pesach
hachishah yatzu, if they walked out of the door that the first
six did, so fine now you've achieved a מעשר, נטלו אחד מהם
והשאר מצטרפים לגורן אחר. natlu echad meihem v'hashar mitztarfum l'goren acher. So
you take the tenth... and
the four that went out of the other door, that was never
מנין הראוי, minyan hara'uy, right, that was never a process that could
have been completed. So they you have to, you have to use
for the next, for the next counting. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, if
they did not go out of that door, they stayed in the
pen, or they went out until it was night and then you
gave up, or they walked out of the door that the other
four went out of, שישה פטורים, shishah peturim, the six that went
out of the first door are exempt because that could have completed
with ten, right, because there were eight left when those six went
out. וארבעה וארבעה מצטרפים לגורן אחר, Ve'arba'ah ve'arba'ah mitztarfim legoren acher, the
other four four are not exempt. The first four that went out
were not part of a process that could have completed, and the
last four were not, did not, you know, were not part of
the מעשר, so those eight you leave over for the next cycle.
Now, that's scenario number one. Let's say the order was reversed. יצאו
ארבעה בפתח זה, Yatza'u arba'ah bepetach zeh, first four went out of
door number one, ושישה בפתח זה, veshishah bepetach zeh, and six went
out of door number two. So let's figure out, when the four
went out of door number one, could that have been a process
that could have been completed? Yes, because there were, you know, there
were ten left. When the six went out of door number two,
could that process have been completed? Yes, yes, because there were four
left. So those four that went out and those six that went
out are both exempt because when they went out the process could
have been completed. And now the only question is what's the story
with the remaining four? Okay.
So it says like this: ונשארו שם ארבעה, Venish'aru sham arba'ah, there
are four left. אם אותם ארבעה בפתח השישה יצאו, Im otam arba'ah
bepetach hashishah yatza'u, if they go out of the same door as
the six, fine, then you've actually achieved מעשר. נוטל מהם אחד והשאר
פטורים. Notel mehem echad vehash'ar peturim.
You take one of those, one of the ten, and the first
four that went out are exempt because that was מנין הראוי minyan
hara'uy when they went out it could have been completed. Excuse me.
What? Even though you're stealing.
Right. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav,
if they don't go out of the door of the six, they
go out of the door of the four, or they just stay
in the pen, ארבעה ושישה פטורים, arba'ah veshishah peturim, the four and
six that went out are exempt because each time when the four
went out it could have been completed, when the six went out
it could have been completed, they were מנין הראוי. minyan hara'uy. But
the last four were never part, if they went out of the
same door as the first four or they stayed in the pen,
they were never part of a מנין הראוי, minyan hara'uy, they were
never part of a counting that could have been completed. וארבעה מצטרפים
לגורן אחר, Ve'arba'ah mitztarfim legoren acher, so the last four get combined
with the next.
What about Rava's point that if one stays in it's the tenth?
But that's only if it's self-evident. It's not self-evident because there's two
countings going on. No, because it might go out the other door.
So it's not clear which, it's a good question, but it's not
clear which group you associate it with.
You're saying it really has to be not just self-evident that it's
the tenth, but which part of the ten it goes towards.
No, because this could be the eighth. It's only the tenth if
you associate it with a particular group. If you associate it with
another group it's the eighth. Okay, and that's only if one's left,
by the way, here four are left. Okay, now, יצאו ארבעה בפתח
זה וארבעה בפתח זה, Yatza'u arba'ah bepetach zeh ve'arba'ah bepetach zeh, let's
say it was four four and then six were left. So when
the first four went out, could it have finished? Yes. When the
next four went out, could it have finished? Yes. Okay, so those
are going to be exempt. And now the question is going to
be the six. So, ונשארו שם שישה, Venish'aru sham shishah, and there's
six left. אם אותם שישה יצאו בפתח אחד, Im otam shishah yatza'u
bepetach echad, now those six, whichever door they go out, they'll be
part of ten, right? So as long as they go out of
a door, so then you're going to take מעשר. נוטל מהם אחד
והשאר פטורים, Notel mehem echad vehash'ar peturim, you take one of them
and the other four are exempt because when they went out that
could have been part of a, that could have been completed. ואם
לאו, Ve'im lav, but if the six refuse to move and you
gave up and you went to bed, it's interesting like at what
stage would it, how far can you continue the process? Anyway, so
then ארבעה ארבעה פטורים, arba'ah arba'ah peturim, the four four are exempt
because when they went out they were part of a process that
could have been completed. ושישה, Veshishah, the six, which were never part
of this process altogether, I mean they never in the end were
part of the process, מצטרפים לגורן אחר, mitztarfim legoren acher, you combine
them. Okay, so that was a lot of fun application, but it's
all the same principle.
Now the גמרא
says, right, what?
Now I would ask Michael's question. What? Really? It's obviously one of
those is going to be the tenth.
Oh, but you don't know which one. I assume that let's say
the better scenario for Michael's question would be you had exactly, you
had nineteen. Nine went out, nine went out, and one was left.
So according to Rava, you know it's the tenth, you don't know
the tenth of which group, right, but the fact that you know
it's the tenth, that might suffice. But here you don't just have
one, you have six. So we can't say anything.
Why wouldn't you say?
Because it's not ten percent, it's the tenth in a sequence.
That's the point. Other than Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, it is not
about ten percent, it is about the tenth in a sequence. So
let's just finish up this point. The גמרא says מאי קמשמע לן,
mai kamashma lan, what's the חידוש? This is all just a straight
application, it was fun, but it's a straight application of Rava's דין.
din. What's the חידוש? דמנין הראוי פוטר, Deminyan hara'uy poter, it's telling
us that being part of a process that could have completed you're
exempt. ואמר רבא חדא זימנא, Ve'amar Rava chada zimna, Rava already told
us.
It says no, it always helps to spell out the scenario.
מהו דתימא, Mahu deteima, I might have
thought ודאי מנין הראוי אמרינן, vadai minyan hara'uy amrinan, definitely מנין הראוי
minyan hara'uy we say. ספק מנין הראוי, Safek minyan hara'uy, when it's
only doubtfully part of the
process, דחזי להכי ודחזי להכי, dechazi lehachi vedchazi lehachi, because it could
have gone either way, לא אמרינן, lo amrinan, you don't say. קמשמע
לן. Kamashma lan. What does that mean? So Rashi says think about
the case about the four four and the six remaining. Okay, when
the four went out, were they part of the second or even...
Wait, let's say the second four went out. Were they part of
the process that could have been completed? Not necessarily. Well, possibly, but
not necessarily. Because if the first remaining six went off to go
down the other door, then it would have turned out that these
four right, if you actually have one single file and something dies,
fine. But at the time that I was counting, there was no
question if the situation would have remained stable, right, there was no
question that they were going to be part of ten. Whereas here
we have four, four and six left. I don't know that the
second four are going to be part of ten because even when
I'm counting them, those other six might choose to go through the
other door. Even if one of those six goes through the other
door, I'm not going to succeed. So maybe the doubtful ראוי roy
is not enough. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that ראוי roy means it
would have been theoretically possible even if not, and even if not
necessarily anticipated or definitely that that would have happened assuming things would
have remained the same. Okay, so that is what that says. What?
It's like saying יש ברירה.
yesh breira. It's like saying אין ברירה. ein breira. Because יש ברירה
yesh breira right, because אין ברירה ein breira would mean that retroactively
they never were part of that process. Right, it's an element of
ברירה breira there.
So if you stay in that door you could exempt all your
animals because...
Yeah,
well you could always do tricks, you could always just not even
bother doing it, which is essentially you're being מבטל המצוה mevatel hamitzvah
but you still... anyways. Let's read one more line, okay, and then
we'll unpack the rest of this statement tomorrow. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava,
Rava also said, היו לו חמשה עשר טלאים. hayu lo chamisha asar
tla'im. If you had fifteen sheep, לא יאמר, lo yomar, do not
say, אעשר עשרה ואכניסם לדיר ואפטור מהם אחד והשאר פטורים. a'aser asara
ve'achnisem ledir ve'eftor mehem echad vehash'ar pturim. Wait, what do you do
when you know that you don't have an exact ten? The fifteen.
So what do you do? Do you say I'm going to leave
five outside, I'm only going to count ten, okay, and then the
other five forget about them? Don't do that. אלא כונסם לדיר, Ela
konsam ledir, put them all in the pen, because you know you
have to sort of
randomize which ten they are, even though it's only going to be
one out of ten, you can't say I'm only going to deal
with ten, you have to deal with all your animals. ומוציא עשרה,
Umotzi asara, you take and ten walk out, ונוטל מהם אחד, venotel
mehem echad, the tenth is
מעשר, והשאר מצטרפין לגורן אחר, vehash'ar mitztarfin legoren acher, and the rest
combine to the next cycle. Now there's two חידושים, chidushim, there's two
ways in which this what's
prescribed is contrasted with what's being rejected. Number one is have all
the animals part of the process, don't leave five on the outside.
But the other thing is Rava says you would have thought that
the five you're not counting are totally exempt from... no, it's not
true. The five that in the end didn't get counted, as long
as it's not ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, have to combine with the
next cycle as long as prior to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and
be combined to get to the next ten.
Which is the same result as if you left them out.
Right, although you would have thought by leaving them out it seems
like... Rava's rejecting what you're thinking in two ways: don't leave them
out and don't think that you're off the hook with those other
five. Okay, and we will continue to unpack this.